There's a big question at the center of life
هناك سؤال كبير في مركز الحياة
in our democracies today:
في الدول الديموقراطية اليوم:
How do we fight terror without destroying democracies,
كيف بإمكاننا أن نحارب الإرهاب بدون تدمير ديموقراطياتنا،
without trampling human rights?
بدون دهس حقوق الإنسان؟
I've spent much of my career working with journalists,
لقد قضيت أغلب مهنتي في العمل مع الصحفيين
with bloggers,
مع مُدّونين,
with activists,
مع ناشطين,
with human rights researchers all around the world,
مع باحثين في حقوق الإنسان من جميع أنحاء العالم.
and I've come to the conclusion
وتوصلت لنتيجة ,
that if our democratic societies do not double down
إذا لم تضاعف مجتمعاتنا الديموقراطية
on protecting and defending human rights,
حمايتها ودفاعها عن حقوق الإنسان
freedom of the press
وحرية الصحافة
and a free and open internet,
وانترنت مجاني ومفتوح,
radical extremist ideologies are much more likely to persist.
الايدولوجيات الراديكالية المتطرفة على الأرجح ستستمر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
OK, all done. Thank you very much.
حسناً, لقد انتهينا . شكرا لكم جزيلاً
No, just joking.
لا ,إني أمزح .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I actually want to drill down on this a little bit.
أريد فعلا أن أُعرّج على هذا قليلا.
So, one of the countries that has been on the frontlines of this issue
إذاً ، واحدة من هذه الدول التي كانت على الجبهة لهذه المشكلة
is Tunisia,
هي تونس,
which was the only country to come out of the Arab Spring
كانت الدولة الوحيدة التي خرجت من الربيع العربي
with a successful democratic revolution.
بثورة ديموقراطية ناجحة.
Five years later,
بعد خمس سنوات,
they're struggling with serious terror attacks
مازالوا يعانون من هجمات إرهابية خطيرة
and rampant ISIS recruitment.
وتجنيد تنظيم الدولة المستشري.
And many Tunisians are calling on their government
العديد من التونسيين يدعون حكومتهم
to do whatever it takes to keep them safe.
لإتخاذ كل مايتطلبه الأمر ، لإبقائهم امنين.
Tunisian cartoonist Nadia Khiari
رسامة الكاريكتر التونسية ناديا خياري
has summed up the situation with this character who says,
لخّصت الموقف بشخصية تقول:
"I don't give a damn about human rights.
"لا أهتم بتاتا بحقوق الإنسان،
I don't give a damn about the revolution.
لاأهتم بتاتا بالثورة,
I don't give a damn about democracy and liberty.
لا أهتم بتاتا بالديموقراطية والحرية
I just want to be safe."
أريد فقط أن أكون بآمان."
"Satisfied?" asked his jailer.
سأل سجّانه "هل أنت راضي؟"
"You're safe now."
"أنت بمأمن الآن."
If the Tunisian people can figure out
إذا تمكن التونسيون من معرفة
how to deal with their terrorism problem
كيفية التعامل مع مشاكلهم بالإرهاب
without ending up in this place,
بدون الانتهاء بهذه الوضعية,
they will be a model not only for their region,
سيكونون قدوة , ليس فقط لمنطقتهم
but for all of us.
بل لجميعنا.
The reality is that civil society, journalists and activists
الواقع أن المجتمع المدني, الصحفيون والناشطون
are coming under attack from extremist groups on the one hand,
من جهة , يتعرضون لهجوم من الجماعات المتشددة ,
and, in many countries,
وأيضا في العديد من البلدن
also from their own governments.
من قبل حكوماتهم .
We're seeing bloggers and journalists being jailed,
نحن نرى مُدّونين وصحفيين يُحبسون
charged and intimidated
يتهمون ويتعرضون للتخويف
by their own governments,
من قِبل حكوماتهم.
many of which are allies with the West in the war on terror.
العديد من تلك الدول هم حلفاء مع الغرب في الحرب على الإرهاب.
Just three examples.
ثلاث أمثلة فقط,
A friend and former colleague of mine,
صديق وزميل سابق لي
Hisham Almiraat,
هشام الميرات
has been charged with threatening state security,
قد اُتهمَ بتهديد أمن الدولة
along with six other activists in Morocco.
مع ست نشطاء آخرين في المغرب.
The Saudi blogger Raif Badawi has been jailed and flogged
المُدّون السعودي رائف بدوي تم حبسه وجلده
for insulting Islam and criticizing the Saudi regime on his blog.
لإهانة الإسلام , وانتقاد النظام السعودي على مّدونته.
More recently, the Turkish representative for Reporters Without Borders,
وفي الآونة الأخيرة , المندوب التركي لمراسلون بلا حدود
Erol Önderoglu,
ايرول اوندار اوغلو
has been detained and charged with spreading terrorist propaganda,
قد اُعتُقَلَ ووجهت إليه تهمة نشر الأجندة الدعائية الإرهابية
because he and some other activists have been supporting Kurdish media.
لأنه وبعض من نشطاء اخرين كانوا يدعمون الإعلام الكُردي.
Anti-terror measures quickly turn into state repression
تدابير مكافحة الإرهاب سرعان ما تنقلب إلى قمع من الدولة
without strong protection for minority communities
بدون حماية قوية للأقليات في المجتمعات
and for peaceful debate;
ولنقاش سلمي؛
this needs to be supported by a robust, independent local media.
هذا بحاجة دعم قوي ومستقل من وسائل الإعلام المحلية.
But while that's not really happening,
وبينما هذا لا يحدث حقاً
Washington is teaming up with Silicon Valley and with Hollywood
واشنطن وكفريق واحد مع سيلكون فالي و هوليوود
to pour millions -- hundreds of millions of dollars --
ستدفق الملايين-- بل مئات الملايين من الدولارات--
into what's called "counter-messaging,"
إلى مايسمى"مكافحة الرسائل"
a fancy word for propaganda.
كلمة فاخرة للدعاية.
To counter the terrorist propaganda spreading all over the internet,
لمواجهة الأجندة الدعائية للإرهابين المنتشرة في كل الانترنت
in Europe, Internet Referral Units are being set up,
في أوروبا ,وحدات إحالة الانترنت يتم انشاءه
so that people can report on extremist content that they find
بحيث يستطيع الناس التبليغ على محتوى متطرف قد وجدوه
and get it censored.
ويتم فرض رقابة عليه.
The problem is,
المشكلة هي
that all of this propaganda, monitoring and censorship
بأن كل هذه الأجندة يتم رصدها ومراقبتها
completely fails to make up for the fact
فشلت تماما في تعويض حقيقة
that the people who are the most credible voices,
أن الناس الذين يمتلكون أصوات ذات مصداقية
who can present credible ideas and alternative solutions
الذين يُمثلون مصداقية الأفكار والحلول البديلة
to real economic, social and political problems in their community
للمشكلات الاقتصادية, الاجتماعية, السياسية الحقيقية في مجتمعاتهم
that are causing people to turn to extremism in the first place,
هم المسبب بتحول هؤلاء الناس لمتشددين في المقام الأول
are being silenced by their own governments.
تم إسكاتهم من قبل حكوماتهم
This is all adding up to a decrease in freedom across the world.
هذا يضاف إلى انخفاض الحرية في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Freedom House,
"فريدوم هاوس"
the human rights organization,
منظمة حقوق الإنسان
reports that 2015 marks the 10th straight year in a row
تفيد التقارير بأن عام 2015هو العام العاشر على التوالي
of decline in freedom worldwide.
في تراجع الحرية في جميع أنحاء العالم.
And this is not just because of the actions
وهذا ليس فقط بسبب الإجراءات
of authoritarian governments.
الاستبدادية للحكومات
It's also because democratic governments
ولكن أيضا بسبب الحكومات الديموقراطية
are increasingly cracking down on dissenters,
التي تزيد الحملة على المعارضين,
whistle-blowers
المبلغين عن المخالفات
and investigative journalists.
وصحفيين التحقيق.
UN Secretary General Ban Ki-Moon has warned
الأمين العام للأمم المتحدة بان كي مون حذر
that "preventing extremism and promoting human rights go hand-in-hand."
بأن "منع التطرف وتعزيز حقوق الإنسان يسيران جنباً إلى جنب"
It's not to say that governments shouldn't keep us safe --
ليس بقول , ليس على الحكومات حمايتنا --
of course they should --
بالطبع يجب عليهم ذلك--
but we need public oversight, transparency
ولكننا بحاجة الرقابة العامة والشفافية
and accountability to the rule of law.
والمساءلة وسيادة القانون.
Meanwhile,
في هذه الأثناء,
extremists are literally killing off civil society in some countries.
المتطرفون يقتلون حرفياً المجتمع المدني في بعض البلدان.
Since 2013 in Bangladesh,
منذ عام 2013 في بنغلاديش
over a dozen secular bloggers and community activists
أكثر من اثني عشر مدونين علمانيين ونشطاء مجتمع
have been literally slaughtered by extremists
ذُبِحوا حرفياً من قِبل المتطرفين
while the government has done very little.
بينما الحكومة لم تفعل شيء يُذكر.
From the city of Raqqa in Syria,
من مدينة الرقة في سوريا,
people like Ruqia Hassan and Naji Jerf have been assassinated
أُناس كـ رقية حسن وناجي جرف تم اغتيالهم
for their reporting out of ISIS-controlled territory.
بسبب تقاريرهم عن المناطق التي تسيطر عليها تنظيم الدولة
The citizen media group called Raqqa is Being Slaughtered Silently
المجموعة الإعلامية المحلية تُدعى الرقة تُذبح بصمت
relies on strong encryption to send out their reports
تعتمد على تشفير عالي لتُرسل تقاريرها
and shield themselves from interception and surveillance.
وحماية أنفسهم من الاعتراض والمراقبة .
Yet authorities in countries like the United States,
رغم ذلك , سلطات في بلدان كالولايات المتحدة,
the United Kingdom and many other democracies
والمملكة المتحدة والعديد من الديموقراطيات الأخرى
are seeking to use the law
يسعون لفرض قانون
to either weaken or outright ban strong encryption,
إما لإضعاف أو حظر التشفير القوي
because the bad guys are using it, too.
لأن الأشرار يستخدمونه أيضاً.
We have got to fight for the right of citizens to use strong encryption.
يجب علينا أن نقاتل من أجل حقوق المواطنين في استخدام التشفير القوي.
Otherwise, dissent and investigative journalism
وإلا , المعارضة والصحافة الاستقصائية
are going to become even more difficult
سيصبحون أكثر صعوبة
in even more places.
في المزيد من الأماكن.
And the bad guys -- the criminals and terrorists --
الأشرار -- المجرمون والإرهابيون--
are still going to find ways to communicate.
سيستمرون بإيجاد طُرق للتواصل.
Kudos to the companies that are standing up
المجد للشركات التي تقف
for their users' right to use encryption.
من أجل حق مستخدميها في استخدام التشفير.
But when it comes to censorship,
ولكن عندما الأمر بالرقابة
the picture is much more troubling.
الصورة أكثر إثارة للقلق بكثير.
Yes, there's a real problem
نعم , هنالك مشكلة حقيقية
of extremist content spreading all over the internet.
في المحتوى المتشدد الذي ينتشر في جميع أنحاء شبكة الانترنت
And Facebook, YouTube and Twitter are among the many companies
فيسبوك, يوتوب, تويتر من بين العديد من الشركات
who report having taken down hundreds of thousands of pieces of content
التي بلغت عن سحب مئات الالاف من قطع المحتوى
and deactivating accounts
وتعطيل الحسابات
that are connected to the extremist's speech.
المرتبطة بالخطاب المتطرف.
The problem is their enforcement mechanisms are a complete black box,
المشكلة تكمن في آليات نفاذهم التي تعد صندوق أسود
and there is collateral damage.
وهناك أضرار جانبية.
Take, for example, Iyad el-Baghdadi,
لنأخذ على سبيل المثال, إياد البغدادي,
an activist who makes fun of ISIS on Twitter.
ناشط يسخر من تنظيم الدولة على التويتر.
He had his account deactivated,
تم تعطيل حسابه
because he shares a surname with a prominent ISIS leader.
لأنه يتشارك الكنية مع زعيم التنظيم البارز.
Last December,
في ديسمبر الماضي,
a number of women named Isis,
عدد من النسوة سموا ايزيس(ISIS)
which also happens to be the name of an Egyptian goddess,
والذي يصادف أيضاً اسم آلهة مصرية,
had their accounts deactivated.
قد تعطل حساباتهم.
And this woman,
وهذه المرأة
who lives in the United States and is a computer programmer,
التي تعيش في الولايات المتحدة , هي مبرمجة حاسوب,
reported on Twitter about her deactivation on Facebook,
تم تبليغها على التويتر بأن حسابها على الفيسبوك تم تعطيله
managed to get enough media attention to have her account reinstated.
تمكنت من الحصول على القدر الكافي من اهتمام وسائل الإعلام ليعود حسابها.
But that's the thing -- she had to get media attention.
لكن هذا هو الأمر -- تمكنت من الحصول على اهتمام الإعلام.
And journalists aren't immune.
والصحفيين ليسوا بمنأى.
David Thomson,
ديفيد تومسون,
an expert on terrorism and reporter for Radio France International,
خبير في الإرهاب ومراسل في راديو فرانس العالمية,
had reports deleted from his Facebook account
تم حذف تقارير من حسابه على الفيسبوك
and had his account deactivated for several days,
وتم تعطيل حسابه لعدة أيام,
because they contained pictures of ISIS flags,
لأنه تضمن صور لعلم تنظيم الدولة,
even though he was just reporting on ISIS,
مع إنه كان يُبلغ عن التنظيم ,
not promoting it.
ولا يروّج له.
And then we have stories from people like this Egyptian man,
ومن ثم كان لدينا قصص من الناس كهذا الرجل المصري,
Ahmed Abdellahy,
أحمد عبدالحي,
who reported recently in an event in Washington DC
الذي ذكرت مؤخراً بحدث في العاصمة واشنطن
that some of his arguments with extremists --
أحد محاوراته مع المتطرفين--
he now spends his time on social media arguing with ISIS followers,
إنه يقضي وقته الآن على وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي يجادل أتباع التنظيم,
trying to get them to turn away --
محاولاً إبعادهم --
some of his arguments with these extremists get deleted,
بعض من جدالاته مع هؤلاء المتطرفين حُذفت,
which he believes has the effect of shielding them
الأمر الذي جعله يعتقد بأنه لديه تأثير يحميهم
from alternative points of view.
من وجهات النظر البديلة.
It's unclear whether Facebook even knows the extent
من غير الواضح ما إذا كان فيسبوك يعرف مدى
of the collateral damage,
الأضرار الجانبية ,
or the other companies as well.
أو حتى الشركات الأخرى كذلك.
But we do know that journalism, activism and public debate
لكننا نعلم بأن الصحافة, النشاط والمناظرات العامة
are being silenced in the effort to stamp out extremist speech.
يتم إسكاته في جهد للقضاء على خطاب التطرف
So with these companies having so much power over the public discourse,
إذاً مع هذه الشركات وهذه القوة على الخطاب الجماهيري
they need to be held accountable.
التي يحتاجونها للمساءلة.
They need to carry out impact assessment
إنهم يحتاجون إلى إجراء تقييم الأثر
to identify and fix the problems that we're clearly seeing.
ليحددوا ويصلحوا المشاكل التي نراها بوضوح.
They need to be more transparent about their enforcement mechanisms,
يجب أن يكونوا أكثر شفافية في آليات نفاذهم,
and they need to have clear appeal and grievance mechanisms,
إنهم بحاجة إلى آليات واضحة في الطعن والتظلم,
so people can get their content reinstated.
ليتمكن الناس من إعادة محتواهم .
Now, I've been talking for the last 10 minutes
الآن , كنت أتكلم في العشر دقائق الماضية
about how governments and companies are making it more difficult
عن ,كيف الحكومات والشركات تجعل الأمر صعبا
for people like these.
لأُناس كهولاء.
This is a picture of members of the citizen media network,
هذه الصورة لأعضاء شبكة إعلام المواطن,
Global Voices,
غلوبال فويسز
that I helped to cofound over 10 years ago
إنني ساعدت على تأسيسها منذ أكثر من 10 سنوات
with my friend, Ethan Zuckerman.
مع صديقي ايثان زوكرمان
Interestingly, about 5 years ago, right after the Arab Spring,
ومن المثير للاهتمام, منذ نحو5 سنوات أي مباشرة بعد الربيع العربي.
the data scientist Gilad Lotan
عالم البيانات جيلاد لوتان
created a network map of the people in Global Voices
خلق شبكة خريطة للأشخاص في غلوبال فويسز
who were heavy users of Twitter during the Arab Spring.
الذين كانوا مستخدمين كثيفين في التويتر خلال الربيع العربي.
And he found that many of these people served as key information nodes
ووجد بأن العديد من هؤلاء الأشخاص قد شغل منصب عقد المعلومات الأساسية
between activists and journalists
بين النشطاء والصحافيين
throughout the Tunisian and Egyptian revolution.
عبر الثورتين التونسية والمصرية.
We've got to make sure that these people not only survive,
يجب علينا أن نحرص على هؤلاء الأشخاص ليس لينجوا فقط ,
but are able to continue to thrive.
بل ليكونوا قادرين على مواصلة الازدهار.
Many of them are still active,
العديد منهم هنا مازالوا ناشطين,
other than the ones who have gone to jail
البعض ذهبوا إلى السجن,
or have been driven into hiding or exile.
أو دُفعوا للاختفاء أو المنفى.
All around the world,
في جميع أنحاء العالم,
people who are sick and tired of fear and oppression
أُناس قد سئموا وتعبوا من الخوف والقمع
are linking up in their communities and across borders.
متصلون بمجتمعاتهم وعبر الحدود.
We've got to do everything we can to push our governments and companies
يجب علينا كل مافي وسعنا لندفع حكوماتنا وشركاتنا
to do a better job of protecting their rights.
ليقوموا بأفضل مايمكنهم لحماية حقوقهم.
We've also got to be more mindful
ويجب علينا أيضا أن نكون أكثر عقلانية
about how our own personal, political, consumer and business choices
لأن خياراتنا الشخصية, السياسية, الاستهلاكية والاقتصادية
affect people like these around the world.
تؤثر على هؤلاء الناس في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Also, if you follow the news,
أيضاً, إذا كنتم تتابعون الأخبار,
it's pretty clear that that alone isn't going to be enough.
إنه من الواضح أن ذلك فقط لن يكون كافياً
We've got to take personal responsibility by joining --
يجب علينا أن نأخذ مسؤولية شخصية بالانضمام--
or at very least, actively supporting --
أو على الأقل , الدعم بإيجايبة--
the growing ecosystem of individuals and groups
المنظومة المتنامية للأفراد والجماعات
who are fighting for social justice,
الذين يقاتلون من أجل عدالة اجتماعية,
environmental sustainability,
استدامة بيئية ,
government accountability,
مساءلة الحكومة,
human rights, freedom of the press
حقوق الإنسان, حرية الصحافة
and a free and open internet,
وانترنت مجاني ومفتوح,
all around the world.
في جميع أنحاء العالم.
I believe that, ultimately, we can overcome
في نهاية المطاف, أعتقد بإمكاننا التغلب
the digitally empowered networks of extremism, demagoguery and hate.
على الشبكات الرقمية المدعومة من المتطرفين ، الديموغاجية والكراهية.
But ...
ولكن ...
we've got to do this by really beefing up the global networks
علينا أن نفعل ذلك حقاً من خلال حشد الشبكات العالمية
of citizens around the world,
للمواطنين في جميع أنحاء العالم,
powered by people who are working hard every day,
المدعومة من الناس الذين يعملون بجد كل يوم,
and taking personal risk
ويتحملون المخاطر الشخصية
for a future world that is more peaceful, just, open and free.
من أجل المستقبل لعالم أكثر سلاماً, أكثر عدلاً, أكثر انفتاحا وحر.
Thanks very much for listening.
شكراً جزيلاً لإصغائكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)